Guide to the Emma Thursby Papers 1706-1942 (Bulk 1860-1940) MS 2530
New-York Historical Society
Emma Thursby papers
1706-1942 (Bulk 1860-1940)
New-York Historical Society
Thursby, Emma Cecilia, 1845-1931
MS 2530
19 Linear feet (25 boxes, 4 bound volumes)
The collection contains information related to the singing career of Emma Thursby and her family relationships. The collection documents the financial and career dealings of a female concert singer in the late nineteenth century.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ina Love Thursby, 1940-1941.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Chronology
February 21, 1845 Birth of Emma Cecilia Thursby, the second of five children (Alice, John, Louis and Ina were her siblings) born to Jane Bennett Thursby and John Barnes Thursby.
1850 Emma Thursby's first concert appearance at the Old Bushwick Reformed Winter Church, to which her family belonged.
1857-1859 Emma and her older sister Alice (also called Allie) study music at the Moravian Seminary in Bethlehem, Pennsylvania.
November 17, 1859 The death of John Barnes Thursby is a financial blow to the Thursby family, and Emma's musical training is put on hold. Emma practices her singing at home with her sisters.
1868-1871 Along with other appearances, Emma is engaged as the soloist at Plymouth Church in Brooklyn, where Henry Ward Beecher is the pastor. Emma Thursby's income is the financial mainstay for the Thursby family from this time onward.
1872-1873 Emma Thursby travels to Italy to train with Francesco Lamperti and Antonio Sangiovanni.
1875 In 1875 Emma Thursby begins studying with Erminia Rudersdorff, her most influential teacher and advisor.
1876 As her national fame grows, Emma Thursby shares a bill at the Brooklyn Academy of Music with Mark Twain, who read from his writings. She also sings at the Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia.
1877 Emma Thursby signs a contract with Maurice Strakosch to be her voice teacher and manager.
1878-1879 Emma Thursby's travels to Europe for her first European concert tour. While in Europe Emma meets Ole Bull, a famous Norwegian violinist, with whom she had forms a close friendship. After Ole Bull's death, Emma remains friends with Sara Bull, Ole's wife, and Olea Bull, his daughter.
1883 Emma purchases an apartment at 34 Gramercy Park and the entire Thursby family moves in.
1884 Death of Jane Ann Bennet Thursby while Emma is on tour in Europe.
1885 Emma Thursby returns to New York shortly before death of her sister Alice.
1893 Emma is invited to be a member of the 'Advisory Council on a World's Congress of Representative Women' at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago. She performs at the Exposition, and meets Swami Vivekananda, a Hindu monk whose teachings she begins to follow.
1889 Emma Thursby first visits Green Acre, an artist community in Maine formed by Sarah Farmer. She also begins holding salons each Friday that function as both social and musical occasions for the musical literati and visiting friends.
January 1899 Death of Emma's pet and traveling companion, Mynah bird.
1895-1924 Emma Thursby once again takes voice pupils.
1903-1904 Emma and Ina Thursby travel to Japan and China.
September, 1918 Death of John J. Thursby.
1924 Emma Thursby suffers a paralytic attack which leaves her left side paralyzed.
July 4, 1931 Death of Emma Cecilia Thursby.
Scope and Content Note
The Emma Thursby Papers consist of material relating to the life and singing career of Emma Cecilia Thursby, as well as the lives of members of her extended family. Included are letters, telegrams, postcards, address books, diaries, engagement books, autographs, calling cards; financial materials including receipts, bills, checkbook stubs, letters of credit; legal papers such as contracts, wills, indentures, and deeds; poetry, programs, periodical clippings, passports, notes, and a few photographs. The collection effectively documents the financial and career dealings of a renowned concert singer in the late nineteenth century. Emma Thursby traveled to many European countries, as well as to Japan and China, both for her career and for pleasure, and most of these trips are well documented. In addition, the many family letters included show the close family network of siblings, aunts, uncles, and cousins that nurtured Emma Thursby.
The bulk of the collection is composed of the Correspondence and the Subjects series. Letters from Ina Thursby to other family members from her travels with Emma provide detailed information on Emma's concert dates, performances, travel, and voice study. The Subjects series highlights Emma's interests after her own singing career had ended such as Eastern religious philosophies or the salons she held every Friday. Specific information about legal and financial aspects of Emma Thursby's career can be found in the Financial or Legal series, but neither of these aspects is as complete a document of her experience as can be found through correspondence.
Arrangement
The Emma Thursby papers have been organized into the following series:
Series I: Correspondence (1839-1940)
Series II: Financial Papers (1706-1919)
Series III: Legal Papers (1788-1903)
Series IV: Address Books, Diaries, Engagement Books (1868-1929)
Series V: Awards, Ephemera, Notes (1850-1936)
Series VI: Subject and Biographical Information (1879-1937)
Series VII: Autographs (undated)
Series VIII: Master Recordings of the Emma Thursby Musicale (1940)
Series IX. Press Clippings and Other Print Matter (1859-1942)
Within each series, the material is arranged either alphabetically or chronologically.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The N-YHS Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections holds the Emma Cecelia Thursby Photograph Collection (PR 126). Photographs of Thursby's family, friends, and colleagues are also included in the Album File (PR 002), Portrait File (PR 052), Theatrical Portrait File (PR 104), Cased Photograph File (PR 012), and Carte-de-Visite File (PR 011).
Awards; Business cards.; Check stubs; Deeds.; Indentures.; Letters (correspondence); Menus.; Notes (documents); Pamphlets.; Passports.; Phonograph records; Place cards; Poems; Programs (documents).; Telegrams.; Wills.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Europe -- Description and travel -- 1919–1944; Europe -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; India -- Religion.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Art, East Asian; Concert agents; Concert tours; Concerts.; Finance, Personal; Music trade; Philosophy, Indic.; Singers.; Singing; Singing -- Instruction and study; Women singers -- United States.; Address books.; Appointment books; Clippings (information artifacts); Contracts.; Diaries.; Letters of credit.; Postcards.; Receipts (financial records); Scrapbooks.; Signatures (names); Visiting cards; Thursby, Ina Love, 1855-; Thursby, Jane Bennett, -1884; Thursby, John Barnes, 1820-1859; Van Cott family; Vivekananda, Swami, 1863-1902; Bennett family; Bull, Ole, 1810-1880; Bull, Olea, 1871-1911; Bull, Sara Chapman Thorp, 1850-1911; Farmer, Sarah J., 1847-1916; Green Acre Fellowship; Jackson, May Howard, 1877-1931; Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; Okakura, Kakuzo, 1862-1913; Ovington, Jeannie; Rudersdorff, Ermini; Strakosch, Moritz, -1887; Thursby (Family); Thursby, Alice, 1843-1886
- Series I: Correspondence, 1839-1940
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence series contains correspondence between Thursby family members, as well as from Emma Thursby's managers, fans, friends, and pupils. The series contains information about important events (mainly deaths) in the lives of the Thursby family members, offers and requests for Emma Thursby to perform, Emma Thursby's participation in the philosophical community Green Acre in Eliot, Maine, and European travelogues and concert reports. This series consists of letters, telegrams, postcards, calling cards, envelopes, and stationery.
  In all her travels Emma Thursby was accompanied by a close family member, perhaps both in the role of chaperone and companion. Her older sister Alice accompanied her on the first tours, and both her mother and Alice went along to Europe in 1878. Emma's younger sister Ina came on this particular trip for only a few months, but would soon accompany Emma on all tours and become her closest companion and confidante. During these later tours it is Ina's letters to the family and friends back in Brooklyn which provide much of the information about the concerts performed, receptions received, friends met, spas visited, and sights seen throughout the years.
  Each correspondence subseries is divided into incoming and outgoing material. Letters are arranged alphabetically by the recipient or sender's name and then chronologically for each person. Correspondents with ten or more letters have separate folders. In addition, correspondents who comprised an entire envelope in the original housing system have been given an individual folder. A few separate folders were also created for important correspondents (such as the Paris Opera) regardless of number of letters.
  Many Thursby family letters are addressed to more than one person (i.e. "Mother, Allie and Lou.") In these cases, the letters have been assigned to the folder of the oldest family member. A letter to "Allie, Lou and John" would be filed under Alice Thursby (the order of children was Alice, Emma, John, Louis, and Ina). Family letters addressed to "Dear sisters" are filed under Emma Thursby.
  For the most part, envelopes are housed with their letters, either inside a card, in an acid-free paper sling, or, if easily identifiable as belonging to the letter, behind the letter. Envelopes that could not be matched to a specific letter are housed in Subseries 8, Other Correspondence.
  - Subseries 1: Emma Thursby, 1859-1931
    The correspondence in this subseries dates from Emma Thursby's days at music school in Pennsylvania as a young girl, and continues until a few days before her death. Her letters to her family from her travels abroad detail her musical education, career, and burgeoning social life on the European continent. Letters to friends such as Sara Bull and her cousin Mary Elizabeth (Mollie) Bennett Comfort also contain thoughts on her life outside her career, and philosophical interests such as Eastern religion.
    Letters from pupils attest to Emma Thursby's popularity as a voice teacher. These letters, most of which are mainly devoted to requesting or confirming dates of lessons, were foldered separately at the time of the accession of the collection, and so have been kept segregated from the other correspondence. Many of Emma Thursby's voice students went on to become operatic or concert stars in their own right; correspondence from these women is contained in Series 6, Subject and Biographical Information; Subseries 1, Emma Thursby. Emma and/or Ina Thursby seems to have kept a file on each of these women, evidenced by the number of clippings and programs kept with these women's correspondence.
    General alphabetical files of correspondence include letters from the following people: Edward Bok, Ole Bull, President Grover Cleveland and family, Count Chinda, Isadora Duncan, P.S. Gilmore, Percy Grainger, Phoebe Hearst, Mrs. Warren Harding, Herman Marcuse, Julia Marlowe, Kate Willard Parker, John D. Rockefeller, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Nicola Tesla, Mark Twain, David Todd, and [Swami] Vivekananda. Letters date from Emma Thursby's entire career, and are both letters of adulation as well as personal correspondence. Performers and pupils represented are Regina Arta (aka Emma Loeffler,) Dula Drake, Emma Eames, Blanche Marchesi, Emma Nevada Palmer, Duchess de Richelieu, Erminia Rudersdorff, and Maurice Strakosch and family. Corresponding institutions (often letters of thanks for concerts given) include Bushwick Reformed Church, Etude magazine, Methodist Episcopal Church South, Musician magazine, Old Bushwick Church, Peabody House for Aged and Indigent Women, and Plymouth Church.
    Many letters are addressed to both Emma and Ina Thursby. These letters, as well as those addressed to "Miss Thursby" have been filed in this subseries, unless clearly identified (based on information in the letter or on original envelope housing) to belong to Ina Thursby.
    The four volumes are red cases labeled "A -- G," "H -- M," "N -- R," and "S -- Z" and contain letters written to Emma Thursby between 1871 and 1910. These letters were item-level cataloged at the time of their accession; a complete listing is available at the reference desk. Some of the correspondents included here (Edward Bok, Sara Bull, Olea Bull, Sarah Farmer, Patrick Gilmore, May Jackson, Jeannie Ovington, Maurice Strakosch, Maggie Van Cott, and [Swami] Vivekananda) also are represented in Boxes 1 -- 5. However, most of these letters were from one-time correspondents. The topics range from thanks given for complimentary concert tickets, to sympathy at the death of Thursby family members.
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from A-B, 1881-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Ralph Bartlett, 1911-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from David Bispham, 1907-1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Sara Bull, 1881-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Olea Bull, 1883-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from C, 1877-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from D, 1901-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from E, 1905-1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from F, 1873-1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Sarah Farmer, 1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from G, 1879-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from H, 1880-1931 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Abraham Hill, 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from I-J, 1892-1913 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from May Jackson, 1887-1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from K, 1904-1921 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from L, 1878-1916 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from M, 1891-1916 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from N-O, 1885-1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from P-Q, 1897-1922 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Paris Opera, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from James B. Pond, 1885-1892 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from R, 1876-1919 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from S, 1877-1924 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Henry W. Shoemaker, 1912-1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from T, 1878-1930 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from J.G. Thorp, 1911-1912 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Alice Thursby, 1881-1885 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Ina Thursby, 1903-1912 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Thursby Family, 1884-1908 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from U-V, 1886-1918 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from W-Z, 1879-1927 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from World's Congress of Representative Women, Exposition of 1893 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Pupils A-M, 1897-1912 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Pupils N-Z, 1898-1927 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Emma Thursby, letters received from Unidentified, 1901-1931 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to A-Z, 1879-1931 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Jackson, May, 1880-1913 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Moore, Mary C., 1887-1903 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Thursby, Alice, 1880-1882 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Thursby, Ina, 1872-1929 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Thursby, Jane B., 1859-1882 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Thursby, John J., 1887-1912 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Emma Thursby letters sent to Thursby, Louis, 1886-1913 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Emma Thursby, letters sent to Thursby Family, 1858-1931 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters received from A-G, 1876-1900 (Volume 1)
    - Letters received from H-M, 1875-1910 (Volume 2)
    - Letters received from N-R, 1871-1895 (Volume 3)
    - Letters received from S-Z, 1876-1900 (Volume 4)
  - Subseries 2: Ina Thursby, 1872-1939
    General alphabetical correspondence files contain letters from Ralph Bartlett, May Jackson, Charles Schwab, and David Todd. Former pupils and associates of Emma's included are Peggy Green (Princess Viggo,) Meta Reddish, Duchess de Richelieu, Amalia Strakosch, Geraldine Ferrar, and Emma Nevada Palmer. Much of the general correspondence letters are condolences to Ina upon the death of Emma Thursby. Ina also planned many memorial events for Emma, including the installation of a mosaic at the Brooklyn Museum of Art; many letters address these projects.
    In 1903, both Emma and Ina Thursby made many friends in Japan with whom they corresponded for years. Letters from Japanese friends in this series discuss visits and friend Kakuzo Okakura's work establishing an Eastern Art wing at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. Letters to family members, especially Alice and her brothers, give great detailed accounts of Ina's first trip with Emma to Europe in 1880 -- 1882.
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from A, 1901-1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from B, 1904-1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from C, 1878-1935 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from Mary Elizabeth Bennett Comfortt, 1931-1938 undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from D-E, 1889-1936 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from F-H, 1908-1931 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from I-L, 1880-1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from M-O, 1899-1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from Kakuzo Okakura, 1904-1912 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from P-R, 1899-1937 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from Shisui Rokkaku, 1905-1908 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from S, 1886-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from Henry Shoemaker, 1931-1937 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from T-Z, 1882-1938 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from Alice Thursby, 1882 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Ina Thursby, letters received from, Unidentified, 1892-1934 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Ina Thursby, letters sent to A-Z, 1886-1934 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Ina Thursby, letters sent to May Jackson, 1898-1912 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Ina Thursby, letters sent to Mary C. Moore, 1886-1891 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Ina Thursby, letters sent to Alice Thursby, 1872-1882 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Ina Thursby letters sent to Jane B. Thursby, 1880-1882 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ina Thursby, letters sent to Louis Thursby, 1878-1907 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Ina Thursby, letters sent to the Thursby Family, 1859-1880 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3: Alice Thursby, 1854-1889
    Consists of letters from Alice Thursby to her aunt Mary C. Moore and to her brothers Louis and John Thursby during her time abroad with Emma. Also contains letters written by Alice to her parents from her time at the Moravian Seminary. Letters to Alice are mainly condolences on the death of her mother.
    - Alice Thursby, letters received, 1884 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Alice Thursby, letters sent, 1859-1878 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 4: Jane B. Thursby, 1870-1882
    Contains correspondence to Jane B. Thursby from her son Louis while he was vacationing in Florida, and a business letter about a monetary settlement granted her.
    - Jane B. Thursby, letters received, 1870-1882 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 5: John B. Thursby, 1839-1859
    Contains letters written between John B. Thursby and his mother Hannah, and brother Samuel, mainly during his trip to France and England just before his death in 1859. Also includes letters written about Emma's musical education, and about John B. Thursby's career.
    - John B. Thursby, letters received, 1839-1859 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - John B. Thursby, letters sent, 1850-1859 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 6: Thursby family letters, 1859-1913
    Contains letters from Louis Thursby to John J. Thursby and a letter to Samuel Thursby from the United States Consulate in London informing him of the death of his brother John B. Thursby.
    - Thursby family letters, 1859-1913 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 7: Mynah Bird, 1892-1894
    Contains letters written to the Mynah bird owned by Emma and Ina Thursby, generally thank you notes to him for entertaining visiting children.
    - Mynah Bird, letters received, 1892-1894 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 8: Other Correspondence, 1861-1940
    This subseries is made up of letters that are not to or from any of the principal members of the Thursby family, as above. People for whom more than ten pieces of correspondence exists were given their own folder. The letters include people who played a large part in Emma Thursby's life, such as her friend Jeannie Ovington, and her friend and manager Maurice Strakosch. Much of the Strakosch correspondence is letters in foreign languages attempting to schedule Emma Thursby concerts. Letters written to Richard Gipson, Emma Thursby's biographer, are included here, as are letters detailing an incident in which a Mrs. Edyth Ellerbeck Read wrote a profile of Emma Thursby and was denied publication by the Ladies' Home Journal.
    General correspondence includes letters to Emma Thursby's Parisian friend May Jackson from Jeannie Ovington, a facsimile of Longfellow's last letter, and letters to unnamed managers of Emma Thursby requesting concert dates.
    One folder of calling cards is in this subseries. Blank stationery with notable letterhead, as well as photography envelopes and letter envelopes which could not be matched with an actual letter, also make up this subseries.
    - A-Z, 1878-1931 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Gipson, Richard, 1937-1940 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Ovington, Jeannie, 1885-1886 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Read, Edyth Ellerbeck, 1905-1912 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Strakosch, Maurice, 1861-1887 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Calling Cards, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Alienated envelopes, Blank stationery, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series II: Financial Papers, 1706-1919
  This series consists primarily of Emma Thursby's financial records dating from 1875 to 1915. Bills, receipts, letters of credit, lists of accounts and expenses make up the bulk of the papers. Most of the letters of credit are from American Express to various foreign banks during Emma Thursby's travels in Europe. Checkbook stubs and small bound account books are included in Box 14. Some of her monetary expenses are also documented in her engagement books in Series 4, Diaries, Address Books, and Engagement Books.